Heat. Hey. Hey. Hey.
Heat. Heat.
Hello everybody. Good day, good evening
to everyone and welcome back to the Ask
Abijit Show. Today we are doing episode
272. I hope everybody is doing
fantastic. Everyone's doing great. Let's
see who all is there on the live stream
on the live chat. I can see Savaria Sait
Ram Shukla from Kpur. New new fan from
Kpur. Welcome sir. Welcome very much
you. I very appreciate I very much
appreciate you being here. Aayush Singh
anonymous scientist Bjour Nabad Tadas
Namaste Kpal Chob Suraj
Aptitude Shoan Bushan Jagdish Mali Kuml
Aush Singh Amisha Mishra Pratam Agarwal
Vikash Vikash PJ Soham Jooshi regular
viewer viewer welcome back sir thank you
so much for for being a viewer. Uh
Kanesh Koshik, Savia S, Alvin Rodriguez,
Ratul Das, Manisha Karoo, Miss Trupti
Explorer 1, Rashmi Ratur from Rajasthan,
Shri Ramchandra, our regular viewer,
thank you very much for being on the
live stream. Abhinav Bishra Hitanchu Ma
from Gujarat welcome Vidhi Manar hello
Sar No Tadas Rashbi again Shashank
Koshik Patrick the killer uh Langi
Suresh Geopolitical Dubet it's raining
okay geopolitical dub from Indor uh who
else do we have Pray Paul from Kolkata
welcome back sir that gour guy who else
do we have Rashi Kudin Deepika Anand
Pai, Rahul Kumar, Dilab, Mitra, Himant,
Kumar, Savary S from Bihar, Alka,
Shikari, Maklavin, Namaste, Somia,
Chaitanya, Manuja, Jay Guman, salut uh
and so many other people. Uh Krishna
from the Sury numbers, Netherlands.
Welcome back, sir. Xya
who else? Pratamarwal veteran 69 indie
who's been following me for three years.
Thank you so much. I really appreciate
that. Kushir Singh, uh, Sujit Sha,
namaste, Lakshai Sharma, Konpal, Chob,
uh, Purveves Khan, hello and everybody
else. Anonymous Cookie Senpai, well,
that's quite a name. Okay, so I'm going
to be taking I'm going to take questions
that you all have asked in the comments
and uh, let's get going with that. Let's
take let's and I'll take as many as
possible over the next couple of hours.
If there is time left over, I'll even
take some questions from the live chat.
We'll see how it goes. Uh the first
question is from Rahul Dunak. If
somebody fires many questions, fires in
many questions in order for one to
stick, is it a good strategy or do you
dismiss all of them thinking that that
the individual is oversmart? Absolutely
not. Ask as many questions as you want.
If you have 30 questions, ask 30
questions. I have no issue with that. I
don't think you're oversmart. You should
have a lot of questions, right? So, I
have no issue with that. But do ask good
questions. That's all. Ask the best
possible questions and I'll try my best
to pick the best ones. And if you have
multiple questions, please ask them
separately. I see many people putting in
a whole paragraph worth of questions. I
won't be able to take those. You have to
ask one question at a time. Uh so yeah,
please go ahead. Do not feel shy. Ask
any question that you have. Okay. With
that said, here we are. So, Prrenet Paul
says, "With the India UK FTA free trade
agreement finally sealed and Prime
Minister Modi's historic UK visit, what
is the real strategic gain for India?
Did the US try to stall this deal
earlier and how might Washington and
Trump now react to this shift in India's
global trade alignment?" Okay, good
question. Excellent question. Give me a
second. uh
so what is the deal with this uh UK
India FTA that we that we have right
what are the parameters of the FDA what
what is what what is the FTA like is
that's the question we want to ask
ourselves so prime minister Modi was
recently in London and that's where he
uh went ahead and concluded signed I
suppose this FDA with the UK's prime
minister Kir Tmer and it's a pretty
comprehensive FDA and it's set to
eliminate most of the tariffs that the
two countries have when trading with
each other. So whatever India is going
to be exporting now onwards to the UK,
all those goods, 99% of the Indian
exports will have no UK tariffs applied
to them. And when it comes to the
British goods that that are exported
from the UK to India, 90% of the goods
will have no tariffs. So it's a pretty
robust pretty strong FTA and uh so
that's that's a pretty good strategic
gain. It means that we can export all
kinds of uh products from India and they
will be very competitive
competitively priced in the British
markets in the UK's markets. That's
great isn't it? So if you want to become
a manufacturing power, if you want to
become an exporting power, then you want
your goods to be competitively priced in
the in the target markets right let's
say you have a nation that applies 20%
tariffs for example hypothetically and
if I have I'm exporting something worth
100 rupees or 100 pounds then it means
that more or less it's going to cost
£120 there so it will not be that
competitive compared to local products
but if there's no tariff
then it's going to be priced exactly at
£100 which is the original price which
makes it more competitive. So that's
great. So that's a significant strategic
gain for India. I mean uh and and so
that's the first thing that's the
straightforward answer that uh this is
strategically great for India and this
obviously gives India leverage. Okay, it
gives India leverage in its negotiations
with the US with the EU. So India
obviously as we know we have this August
1 deadline that the Americans have
imposed on India uh for finalizing an
interim trade deal with the Americans
right uh so we can showcase this to the
US. Look we have been able to uh bring
about this fantastic agreement with the
UK. So if there are problems when it
comes to the uh trade negotiations
between the US and India, maybe there's
a problem with you guys, with the
Americans, maybe you are adopting
maximalist stances. Look at the UK. We
are the same guys negotiating with the
UK and we have been able to successfully
bring about this fantastic agreement. So
it gives us more leverage. It also gives
us leverage visa with other countries
visa with the EU and so on. We also have
trade agreements that are that have
happened between us and Australia and
there's more to come. Uh so it's
fantastic you know um and this also uh
there's this there's this narrative
that's been created on social media in
uh opinion pieces in think tank articles
uh and so on that there is this east
versus west divide right and India is an
eastern nation and India is is something
you know that that sort of thing so we
can once again showcase this deal to
demonstrate that look we don't believe
in an east versus west divide we are a
multi-aligned nation and our
multi-aligned approach is successful
right and you can see that we've been
able to to achieve this landmark deal
with the UK and also with Australia and
we're going to be doing it for with
other nations so there is no such thing
as an east versus west divide we're not
part of this block or that block or this
group or that group we are multi-aligned
uh so this is a significant boost for
India and it's going to give India
leverage over the US. It's going to give
India leverage over other nations with
whom we have ongoing trade negotiations.
So I think it's fantastic. I don't know
if the US tried to stall this deal
earlier. Um how might Washington and
Trump now react to this shift in India's
global trade alignment? uh it's
obviously going to be noticed and noted
in Washington and uh now the onus is
going to be on the US to finalize an
inter trade deal with India by August 1
and if they if it doesn't happen then we
can certainly tell them that you know
what you guys have been obstructionist
maybe you guys have had u maximalist
stances all or nothing that sort of
thing and we obviously
we're not going to uh give
to your bullying or arm twisting or s
such things. So, uh it's definitely good
for India. It's it's great for India and
it's going to give us leverage over the
it's going to give us leverage in our
trade negotiations with the Americans
mainly the Americans also the EU. It
sets a precedent that look we've we went
ahead and we did this with the UK. Now,
let's do it with the EU. Let's do it
with the Americans. Whoever we are
negotiating with, we can showcase this.
Look, we achieved this. So, why can't we
achieve it here with our negotiations?
So overall it's fantastic. It has you
know multiple benefits for India. So
overall great very pleased to see this.
All right. What other questions? Next
question.
Okay. Rakesh says how do you see the
trade deal deal between the US and
Japan?
Is it a win-win deal? And how do you see
the India? Okay. We spoke about the
India and UK trade deal. Let's talk
about uh the US and Japan. So let us put
out I mean I haven't seen the you know
studied this in detail but I can show
you this and this should be a good
enough indicator as to what the deal is
like. So this is Donald Trump's truth
social account in which uh he has spoken
about this deal. So this was on July
23rd. Today is July 26th 3 days ago.
That's when he put out this uh social
media post. We just completed a massive
trade deal with Japan. Perhaps the
largest deal ever made. Japan will
invest at my direction $550 billion into
the United States which will receive 90%
of the profits. Does this look like a
win-win trade deal to you? US The US
will receive 90% of the profits. The
Japanese will invest $550 billion into
the US. This is a big win for the US and
the US will receive 90% of the profits.
That's what Trump is claiming. If that
is correct, then it's not a win-win
situation. It's heavily skewed in favor
of the US. Now, let's read forward. Uh,
this deal will create hundreds of
thousands of jobs in the US. Of course,
there has never been anything like it.
Perhaps most importantly, Japan will
open their country to trade including
cars and trucks, rice and southern other
agricultural products and other things.
Japan will play will pay reciprocal
tariffs on the US of 15%. reciprocal
tariffs which means that Japan will also
impose 15% tariffs on American products.
So that is that is balanced. It's 15%
both ways that is fine. Uh this is a
very exciting time for the US for the
United States of America especially for
the fact that we uh will continue to
always have a great relationship with
the country of Japan. Of course they are
your you occupy them militarily they
have no choice. So obviously it's going
to be a great relationship for you not
for Japan.
For Japan it's not a great relationship
for you. for the US. It's a great
relationship. Thank you for your
attention to this matter. And then he
goes ahead and says this as well. Let it
load. Remember, Japan is for the first
time ever opening its market to the US.
Uh even to cars, SUVs, trucks, and
everything else, even agriculture and
rice, which was always a complete no. My
god. My god. The Japanese are opening up
their market to American agricultural
products. That is a disaster for Japan.
We'll discuss why it's a disaster. the
open trade, the open market Japan may be
as big a profit factor as the tariffs
themselves, but was only gotten because
of the tariff power. So, he's boasting
how strong his arm twisting tactics are.
That's what Trump is doing here. They
also agreed to pay billions of dollars
worth of military and other equipment
and give us 90% of $550 billion and
more. MAGA, maga, maga, right? Does this
look like a fair deal? A win-win balance
deal? No. It's all pro- US. 90% of the
profits will go to the US of these $550
billion that Japan will be investing
into the US. U and Japan is going to buy
billions and billions of dollars worth
of American military equipment and other
equipment. This is nothing but paying
tribute. Now what do I mean by paying
paying tribute? when you had the Roman
Empire when you had other empires and
they had vasals so the Roman Empire had
let's say Judea as it as it was vasal or
or whoever else then those states those
wasal nations had to pay annual tribute
to the Roman Empire which would be
either in the form of a certain quantity
of gold every year or a certain quantity
of wheat or agricultural produce every
year or a certain quantity of slaves
every year or maybe a combination of all
three or and other factors as well
that's called an annual tribute that you
pay to your overlord if you are a wasal.
Now in today's world you can't make it
so so clear that you are taking tribute
from your vasal. So you you couch it in
this sort of language that you know
we're going to sell stuff to Japan and
Japan will buy billions and billions of
dollars worth of this and that and
that's tribute and the profit obviously
90% plus will remain with the US. So
there you have it. It's it's nothing but
a vasal paying tribute to its overlord.
That's the thing. And Japan has opened
up its market. It's going to open up its
market to agricultural products in the
US. The American Have you seen the state
of
the US population's health? It's
horrible. It's terrible. The US The
United States has the unhealthiest
population on the planet. diabetes,
obesity, cancer, god knows what other
illnesses. People pop pills every single
day. There's no individual in the US who
doesn't pop pills every day, right? One
pill to balance the effects of another
pill and so on so forth. It all stacks
up. Why is it so? Why is the food Why
are why is everybody sick? It's because
of the of the food, the agricultural
products and and whatever else. It's
extremely unhealthy. all genetically
modified, engineered and whatnot. Um,
and if you if you import that from the
US and feed that to your population,
your population is going to fall sick
and you're going to have the same
effects.
Um, and of course then there's the
painted patented products like um if if
they sell you rice for example,
genetically modified rice, then the
patent of the rice remains with the
American companies, which means they own
the rice.
So if you take the rice seeds and re
replant them, then they're going to take
a share of the profits. Whatever
happens, it's it's terrible. It's
terrible. And that's why India has been
opposing India has been pushing back
against the US in our trade negotiations
with the US because the Americans want
us to open our markets or market to
their agricultural products which are
which is a big no no for us. But the
Japanese have well they have been forced
into this. This is not a good trade
deal. This is a horribly lopsided trade
deal similar to what the Americans have
done with Indonesia for example. We
spoke about that some time ago. Uh so
yeah, that's what happens when you are a
vasal and you have no leverage. This is
what happens to you. Remember that's why
sovereignty is so important. So this is
a terribly lopsided trade deal.
Extremely unfair, extremely unbalanced.
the US will
uh get 90% or more of the profits.
Terrible.
Okay. General says, "What can we what
can we theoretically do if tomorrow,
let's say, the US puts 500% tariffs on
us like they've been threatening?" Okay.
What leverage does India have except for
the Chinese angle? Right. So, let's look
at this hypothetical scenario. 500% UF
US tariffs on Indian goods. What could
India do? So first of all look at the
things that India has. We India has this
huge services export market that we
control right particularly in BO
business process outsourcing in the IT
field of of course right major American
corporations like Microsoft, Google etc.
Almost every American fortune 500
company all of these companies they
heavily depend on Indian technological
talent and service centers. So if the
Americans impose 500% tariffs on India
we could immediately disrupt this and
this could immediately impact these
corporate oper operations. So that's
number one. Then pharmaceutical
dependency. India exports about supplies
about 40 to 50% of America's genetic
drugs. So whatever generic drugs the
Americans export import about 40 or 50%
of that comes from India. Okay. And if
we restrict that that would create an
immediate healthcare crisis in the US
and that would be tremendously bad for
Donald Trump because he will be blamed
for that. Right? The Republicans will be
blamed for that. You imposed 500%
tariffs on India and that's why India
retaliated. India is not going to sit
back and just take it. Right? then we
could impose retaliatory tariffs,
reciprocal tariffs on the US u whatever
it is energy exports agricult we don't
import agriculture products obviously
but uh whatever else so that's another
thing so we could uh shut down the the
IT thing we should we could shut down
obviously it'll hurt India also no
question about it but yeah it'll create
a crisis in the big American companies
it'll create a healthcare crisis in the
US immediately
Um then let's say India revokes all H1B
visa processing. Okay, that would
the US tech sector in weeks or
months, right? Because the US tech tech
industry, the IT industry, the tech
industry overall, it employs hundreds of
thousands of Indian professionals and
these cannot be easily replaced. Let's
say we we say that all H1B visas are
revoked with immediate effect. Okay. and
all Indians who are on H1B visas their
visas are null and void. We could do
that. Then what does the US do? We we
mandate that all Indian citizens who are
on H1B visas need to return to meet
India immediately.
We could create that sort of situation
right or so that's that's one thing we
could do. Now these are these are
reciprocal actions we could take in
various ways. There's geopolitical
actions also that we can take. We could
unilaterally withdraw from the Quad
alliance. We could restrict whatever
military access the US has to Indian
facilities, airports or whatever for
refueling or whatever. So that we could
do that that India is is a critical
component of the American Indo-Pacific
strategy visa with China, right? So we
could withdraw from the quad. We could
deny US access to Indian facilities,
the US, UK, whoever. No, not the UK, US
probably. Yep. Uh then we could pivot
towards deeper economic integration with
Russia and China beyond what we're doing
already. Um and there's some kind of
yeah diplomatic activity already going
on between India and China, right? So
that's what we could do. That would not
be great for the US. We could also block
US initiatives in multil multilateral
forums like the G20, the UN, wherever
else, right? we could accelerate our
trade uh agreements with the EU, with
Australia, Australia, the Middle East
nations and so on and and so much more.
Uh
and then we could uh we could have
deeper integration with BRICS nations.
That that's another thing we could do.
Um we could limit access
uh see American digital companies, they
have operations in India. We could
create
uh situations where they will have to
localize the data within India. We'll
have to we can we could increase the
compliance requirements for operating in
India. We could limit market access to
various American companies. So much
more. So there is so much India can
theoretically do if the US
hypothetically
imposes 500% tariffs on India. It's not
like India doesn't have any leverage. So
the US is very well aware of this and
that's why the trade negotiations are
going on. There was an earlier deadline
I think I forget the date whatever it
was that came and went nothing happened.
No trade deal happened. Now the
Americans are saying that this this new
headline this new deadline that they
have unilaterally imposed which is uh
August 1. We'll see how it goes. We'll
see how it goes. We don't have to accept
any of their uh unilaterally imposed
deadlines. And of course this 500%
tariff threat it's it's about India
purchasing oil from Russia and they're
not happy about that. Well boohoo
we are reexporting it to the to the
Europeans aren't we? Europeans are
buying it. The EU is buying it. So they
need something that we are offering. So
we are getting it in this manner. That's
up to us. We are a sovereign nation and
uh so yeah so that's that's the
situation right now. They are
threatening that they will impose 500
tariffs, 500% tariffs on us if we
continue with the oil imports from
Russia. We'll see about that. We have
plenty of leverage. It will hurt us too.
No question. But it's not like it will
not hurt them either. So that's where we
are.
Now let's talk about India and China of
course. So anonymous scientist says why
is China suddenly cozing up to India? Is
it because of the US's trade war and the
US influence on Pakistan which could be
detrimental to Chinese interests? What
should India do? Could this be a trap
for India? And Supraati data says we
have seen rising tensions between India
and China due to his holiness the Lama
issue the Akash prime test near LC not
not the Akash prime test but anyhow and
this must have been in India's
retaliation to China's open support to
Pakistan but India have has recently
opened up visas for Chinese nationals.
Is it due to western sanction threats to
send a message that all doors are not
closed? You have previously said that
China won't be changed. Should we trust
China as a reliable partner, strategic
partner? What should what will be the
future of the India China uh
relationship? Okay. So this look, we can
trust China. We can trust China to
prioritize its own interests. We can
trust China to prioritize its national
interests first always. That in that
sense, we can certainly trust China. So
if we understand what their perception
of their interests is then we have a
very good idea of how they're going to
behave and that's that's what I do. Uh
so in that sense we can certainly trust
China. Uh, of course, we have to
remember that India and China because of
China's occupation of Tibet, uh, we are
strategic rivals just like China and
Russia are long-term strategic rivals
because they have a long, very long uh,
common border, right? Uh, that we have
to remember. But India and China are
both facing a tremendous amount of heat
from the US. Different kinds different
kinds the American approach to China is
different from the American approach to
India or Russia. So India, Russia,
China, all three are facing a lot of
heat from the US, right? The US is it
doesn't necessarily want India to become
a great nation in the in the future. The
US wants India to remain where it is. It
is not in the American interest to see a
great India, a resurgent India uh emerge
on the horizon. And historically, if you
look at the history of the past 2,000,
5,000 years, India has always been the
largest economy. So that is India's
natural position in the world. Even if
you can't imagine it today,
even if you can't imagine it, India's
natural position in the global order is
is has always been that of the largest
economy and that's a problem for the US
and China is currently threatening to
emerge as the largest economy for now.
That's a problem for the US and China
and India are very different nations. So
they are applying different kinds of
heat on India and China.
uh and and as we know there's this
tremendous trade war that's happening
between the US and China and the
decoupling has already more or less
happened and the US market is now off
limits more or less to to the Chinese.
So what do the Chinese do? They have
this enormous manufacturing over
capacity. What do they do with it? Well,
it makes sense to export stuff to India,
right? Because India is the only other
nation that has an enormous market and a
growing market.
So it makes sense for China to to some
extent normalize relations with India.
Um but the Chinese as we know they have
their own interests and they've been
supporting Pakistan in a variety of ways
and they're pretty open now about it. In
the past they've been cy about it but
now they're open about it and that's why
we have gone ahead with other things
like imply like like imposing uh
pressure on China visa with the via the
Tibet issue the issue of the
reincarnation of his holiness the Dalai
Lama all of that and that obviously will
make China behave most of you will think
that if we do these things China will
get angry and then the relations can't
improve no that this is how relations
improve by demonstrating the kinds of
leverage you have over them that's how
you make them behave. This is not a way
of making relations worse. It's a m it's
a way of explaining to your dance
partner the kind of leverage you have
and that's when you can recali that's
when both partners can recalibrate uh
how things are and then we can dance.
That's how it goes.
uh but we have to remember that China
will always see India as an adversary
and we have to that's that's why we have
to be very careful about China and I've
always said that uh so is something a
trap for India not necessarily not
necessarily now there is talk of ra
again I mean few weeks ago I had this
episode on on
I think geost strategy most likely in
which I explained in detail with a
tremendous amount of historical
precedence that China has always been
the spoiler when it comes to bricks and
ra. So now the onus is on China. You
know there's this talk of ra again and
they are they the Chinese are having the
Russians talk about ra right now because
they want to revive the the the concept.
Well that's fine. It's good but it will
all depend on China's attitude and
behavior. So overall my the point is
that if China is and and there are other
manifestations of China co like you say
cozying up to India. Now they're trying
to to some extent normalize relations
with India. I think and I suspect
there's a lot of
lot of diplomatic activity happening.
Okay, India and China are talking to
each other right now. It may not be
visible. It may not be announced but
there there's a lot of back and forth
happening right now. There's a lot of
negotiating happening right now
and some of that we will discuss uh
imminently in the question after this
one. Uh so all of that is going on and
uh the reason for this obviously is the
bigger factor which is the United
States. So the Chinese will not give up
whatever leverage they have over India
when it comes to Pakistan. The
Pakistanis are to some extent aligned
with Pakist with China to a much larger
interest the extent they're aligned with
the Americans. Of course the Americans
operate Durkhan air base and the
Pakistani nuclear deterrent is most
likely an American nuclear deterrent
which has been given to Pakistan to you
to to counterbalance India most likely
it's that so China and and America the
US they both see eye to eye when it
comes to Pakistan and India they both
see Pakistan as as a viable asset to be
used against India to counterbalance
India and to to destabilize India
whenever required
so that's the situation but China is
facing the hate from the US and And
that's not going to go away. India is
facing the heat from the US. That also
is not going to go away. The US will uh
play its game. It doesn't want China to
to grow beyond what it's already grown.
And it doesn't want India to to emerge
as the next China in the next 20 years.
So the US is containing both India and
China. So it makes sense for India and
China and Russia, three of them to dance
together. tango minata like they say in
French notwa but you know trilateral
tango let's say yeah u but of course
India will have to be very careful when
it comes to China so we will always have
to keep on verifying what they're up to
and uh yeah so that's the situation so I
think the future dynamic of the India
China relationship is going to be more
of a trilateral dynamic possibly India
China Russia and Russia could be the
stabilizing factor Russia could be the
factor that you know keeps the two the
to
get gets them to behave especially China
obviously. So yeah that that seems to be
the future the next 10 20 years the see
the biggest issue when it comes to India
and China is the Chinese occupation of
Tibet. India and China have never been
neighbors for the past 2,000 years. Then
in the 1950s the Chinese occupy Tibet
and that's how India and China suddenly
get a common border and that's an
undemarcated border that the Chinese
don't want to demarcate and that's the
main issue. So what happens? How do how
can India and China normalize the
relationship to a certain extent? One
straightforward answer is that China
should agree to de demarcating the
border the India Tibet border and that
should set all problems addressed but
they don't want to do it. They don't
want to because they want to have that
leverage over India. We are more
powerful than you. We occupy the higher
ground and in Chinese occupied Tibet and
the border is undemared so we can keep
on claiming various pieces of your
territory. That's the that's the big
leverage they have.
So maybe we can agree that we're going
to keep the border issue aside for the
next 10 years, 20 years, whatever.
Otherwise, it's not going to work out.
So we'll have to see how it goes. The
Chinese will not agree to demarcating
the border. I'll be very surprised. I'll
be happy, but I'll be very surprised if
that happens. So as long as the border
is not demarcated, we have to keep the
Tibet issue open and you know, remind
the Chinese that, you know, we don't
consider Tibet as part of China. Tibet
obviously Tibet has never been part of
China. So yeah, it's complicated and
that's how it's going to go for the time
being.
Right, next question.
Okay, we have a bunch of questions all
about the Maldives. What has changed
says Danush in the India Maldives
relationship where Maldives went from
being anti-India to suddenly pro-India?
Is Maldives still now a Chinese proxy or
is it pro- India now? Miranka Seeker
Biswar says Prime Minister Modi's recent
visit to the Maldives marked by a
military salute and state honors signals
a remarkable diplomatic turnaround
especially after the strong India out
sentiment just a year ago their their
leader Mr. Mizu was the uh was at the
forefront of this India out uh campaign
wasn't he and right now is
receiving Prime Minister Modi at the
airport giving him grand welcome and all
right so what specifically leverage or
strategic tools do you think New Delhi
employed to engineer the shift in
Mallay's posture prenipal says with
prime minister Modi receiving a grand
welcome in the Maldives after the
hostile India out campaign and extending
a 4850 cr credit line how do you assess
the strategic importance of this visit
Could India's handling of this
turnaround be seen as a case study of in
foreign policy majority especially in
the face of rapid geopolitical changes
around the world? Okay.
So all of this is being asked. There
have been more questions about the
Maldives. I've only taken three there as
as representative questions. A lot of
people have asked questions about the
Maldives. Uh Prime Minister Modi has
tweeted more than 25 times about the
Maldives visit in the past day or so.
Actually, it's more than 30 times now on
his Twitter account, X account. So
what's going on? That's the question. So
what's changed? So first of all, let's
remember what's happened. There was a
pro- India friendly to India government
in Maldives which went out of power. A
new new leader came in Mr. Muizu and he
came to power on a very strongly
anti-India campaign. India out. He had
this t-shirt he was wearing. India out.
Do we have that? Let me see if we can if
we can find that. India out. Mr. Muizu.
Uh anyhow I'll not go and put that on
the screen because it's not important
but he had this very strong anti
anti-India campaign and that's what
brought him to power and he has been
very strongly pro-China. So Maldiv has
always been this contested ground in the
Indian Ocean region where China has been
trying to increase increase its
influence even Sri Lanka but let's talk
about Maldives. So there have been
pro-China governments then pro India
governments and again prochina then
again pro- India it's been back and
forth like that in the maldives and Mr.
Muisu has been historically very
pro-china and very strongly anti-India
and he took all kinds of steps to get
India out of the Maldives. So some
Indian military personnel were were
stationed in the Maldives as technical
personnel to to uh maintain some
aircrafts that we had donated to the
Maldives. those Indian military
personnel were asked to leave. Certain
certain contracts that were given to
development infrastructure contracts
that had been given to Indian companies,
those were revoked by Mr. Muiz's
government and so on. So and and the
Maldivian government, Mr. Muiz's
government, they acquired some Turkish
drones recently and they have given
contracts that were canceled for Indian
companies. Those those contracts were
given to Chinese companies. So overall
it's been very strongly pro-China and
very anti-India
and I suspect there could be a religious
angle to this as well. Right. Possibly.
Possibly. So what's happened now? What
happened? The guy went from being
totally anti-India to welcoming Prime
Minister Modi, hugging Mr. Modi at the
airport and and putting up a gigantic uh
uh poster of Mr. Modi on the defense
ministry building and and very warm
welcome to Mr. Modi and all kinds of
agreements have been signed. What
happened is the question. Is Maldiv
still a Chinese proxy or is is it back
with India now? I suspect is still Mr.
Buizu and his government are still a
Chinese proxy. I suspect they still are.
Then then what happened? That's the
question. That's what I was talking
about just a while ago that India and
China they are most likely quietly
talking diplomatic activity back and
forth. This negotiations happening. You
want this? I need this. Let's talk. What
can you give me? What can you offer me?
What can I I offer you? What do we want?
What do we try? What do we want to
achieve? Okay, you want better
relations. Talk to Maldives. Get them to
go back to, you know, go back to being
friendly with India. That that's
possibly something something that could
have happened. So, I think Mr. Muizu is
possibly still a Chinese asset,
but because of the changed situation
between India and China, maybe this has
come about. Let's just put it that way,
right? Um and obviously this has
happened because of the diplomatic
maturity that India has shown. Mr. Muizu
has had a very strongly very very very
strongly anti-India campaign. He has
been extremely unfriendly towards India
in the past. Right? But India did not
ever respond officially like that in in
response to that. The Indian government
did not make any anti-maldiv statements
any the Indian government did not make
any anti-mouizu statements. the Indian
government's uh signaling and messaging
was very calm completely ignored the
negative messaging coming from the
Maldives right so by adopting this
mature posture and position today we are
able to achieve to to achieve u what we
what we have achieved through the p
visit visit of prime minister Modi to to
the Maldives so it is diplomatic
maturity even when things are like this
you don't respond you don't lash out you
don't act immaturely
like a teenager. Yeah, you don't do
that.
So that's what India has done. Um what
other questions do we have?
So it's pretty strategically
significant. Uh I I suspect I I expect
that you know
India's uh there's going to be more
developments in the India Maldives
relationship. Maybe some development
projects may once again be given to
Indian companies. um and u so on we'll
have to see about that but this is a
very mature approach that India has
taken to the Maldives so I think that
this has happened because of the
situation because of the evolving
situation between India and China and
China must have said that they're okay
with India with Maldi is no longer being
anti-India that sort of thing so that's
most likely what's happened so it's it's
great it's very mature diplomacy very
mature foreign policy from India
excellent
Okay, multiple questions about Thailand
and Cambodia. First of all, if you want
to understand what's going on, please
watch episodes 11 and 14 of Geost
Strategy in which I've explained the
situation in great detail. In episode
11, I've spoken about the historical
context of this issue, the Thailand
Cambodia border dispute. And in episode
14 that aired last night for u in that
I've spoken about what has recently
happened, the the recent
um conflration the recent escalation in
the issue which came out of century
nowhere. Uh so Shri Ram Chandra says
Thailand has more military advantages
compared to Cambodia. How to stop this
from turning turning into a war? Should
India play a role in this? After all,
it's a Hindu temple. Well, India is not
not officially a Hindu nation by the
way. The government of India is
officially a secular government.
So even if it's a Hindu temple, well, we
are no longer a Hindu nation. You see?
So we no longer have that moral high
ground of being a Hindu nation and
that's why that we are a Hindu nation
that's why we should go and mediate and
put an end find a way for both sides to
put an end to the fighting you can do
that only if you are an officially Hindu
nation then you have the moral authority
to do that that India is a secular
nation so so forget about that being a
Hindu temple and secondly
this is no longer a conflict about the
temple it's gone beyond that there
there's been military action
in parts of the border that have nothing
to do with the temple far from the
temple also. So uh the whole conflict
originated as a conflict about the
ancient Shiva temple the Priya Vihar
temple which was built which the
construction of that started about 1100
roughly years ago by the Kir king Surya
II
who built the Ankorwa temple also in
Cambodia. Uh so he was a great king and
the construction went on for about 100
200 years and today the temple is
ruined. Uh
nobody there's no active worship as as
far as I know happening over there but
it is still highly re this temple is
still very highly revered in both
nations. So both nations want this
temple and the territorial dispute
happened because of the actions taken by
the French colonizers who occupied the
region and long history. If you want to
understand the history, you can look at
episode 11 of geost strategy. So uh and
and the UN also the international court
of justice also gave some judgments
which were kind of ambiguous and so on.
So that's why this entire thing is
continued.
Um now the question is is this
geopolitically significant? Does it
affect the interests of the US, China or
India, the Southeast Asia nation and
what's the reason behind the recent
flare up between the two nations? Is it
a just a border issue or is there
something deeper going on like the case
of Manipur and project Kilan for Christ
project K which is a proxy conflict
right uh and can India or China do
anything sign anything about this
conflict okay
so this conflict was about this temple
should I go to the map well why not
let's let's put the map on the screen
because it's always a good idea to take
a look at the map so let's put the map
on the screen
um here's the map we go to our
neighboring countries over here Thailand
is a neighboring country in case you're
not aware we have a maritime boundary
with Thailand right across the Andaman
Sea we have Thailand
um over here Suratani and uh Puket and
so on not far so we have Thailand and
east of Thailand you have Cambodia
right they have a significantly
reasonably long border now let's go to
the Priya Vihar
Priya Priya the
her temple. So it's going to zoom in. So
it's a pretty big temple and the Indian
government is involved in some of the
restoration activities of this temple.
It has been this temple is on a hillside
as you can see
uh pretty big temple pretty big temple
as you can see multiple gapuras four
goas
uh and so on. So this is a temple that
sits on the border between the two
countries and this has officially been
given to Cambodia by the International
Court of Justice. As you can see it
falls within Cambodia and there are
other temples also in this region, Hindu
temples that are kind of desired by both
countries.
So that is the situation. But now the
fighting is happening in other parts of
the border also far from the temple.
So it started as a temple dispute. Okay.
It started as a dispute about a temple,
nothing more than that. But now it's
gone some it's become something bigger.
So what is the situation? So this all
started. So there have been multiple
phases of fighting over the years
between the two countries. I think 2008
2009 there was a big flare up but then
it was contained eventually. Now there's
a bigger flare up because the Thai
government has employed F-16s to conduct
air strikes on Cambodian military
targets. I mean that's a huge
escalation.
Uh so look Cambodia
understand the history okay once again
we go to the map to understand the
history we have to look at the map okay
I I'll explain the history so in the
1970s what happened is that uh okay here
we are I'll so we have Cambodia we have
Thailand we have Laos and we have
Vietnam these are some of the most
important nations in the ASEAN region
Southeast Asia region another is
Myanmar. Of course, in the 1970s,
the Chinese had a proxy fighting force
called the Kir Rouge, which were
communist movement. And the Kam Rouge
was supported unfortunately by
Cambodia's crown prince Shri Naratam
Sihanuk.
And the Kamir Rouge, which was a Chinese
proxy, it was able to take control of
Cambodia in the 1970s, second half
roughly of the 1970s.
And they conducted a horrific genocide
in Cambodia. Absolutely horrific. You
can't imagine what they did in Cambodia.
And eventually Vietnam stepped in.
Vietnam is a communist nation. They
stepped in and they liberated Cambodia
and they kicked the K Rouge out of
power.
Now Vietnam is a communist nation. They
kicked a communist movement, communist
uh government out of power. the Kome
Rouge government which was supported by
China. In response, the Chinese
responded by invading Vietnam to punish
Vietnam. But surprisingly, Vietnam gave
China a bloody nose and kicked the
invading army, people's liberating
liberation army out. It was a
humiliating defeat for China. So since
then,
Vietnam has kind of been a big brother
to Cambodia.
Then eventually Cambodia got a new new
governments which kind of aligned with
China to some extent. Okay. Um and the
strong man of Cambodia for the past 20
30 years has been Mr. Hunen. And today
he is no longer the leader of Cambodia.
His son is the leader of Cambodia but
the real center of power is obviously
still Mr. Hunen. Um so Cambodia is kind
of you could say aligned with China to
some extent. Thailand is aligned with
the US. The Chinese have invested
billions of dollars in both countries
for their built and road initiative.
There are Cambodian workers, maybe tens
of thousands, maybe even more who work
in Thailand. There is significant
crossber trade. Thailand has a much
stronger military compared to Cambodia.
Thailand is much more prosperous
compared to Cambodia. Um,
and that is the situation. So hopefully
this explains. So now the when it comes
to Vietnam and Cambodia, Vietnam is kind
of a big brother to Cambodia. So it is
uh it's a complicated relationship to to
one the Cambodians do recognize the fact
that Vietnam saved Cambodia, but they
also find Vietnam kind of an overbearing
bigger brother to some extent. So it's a
complicated relationship.
So now the two nations Thailand and
Cambodia are on the brink of war.
And if that happens well Thailand will
So how did this thing happen? It
happened because there was a phone call
between the Thailand Thai Prime Minister
Pang Ton Finawatra and Mr. Hunen the
strongman of Cambodia and Mr. Hunen
recorded this phone call and he leaked
it and in that phone call she is she
kind of criticizes some uh the Thai
military and she calls him uncle and
she's very differential to him and
that's why she got suspended by the Thai
government. So she's no longer the prime
minister right now. Um in Thailand, you
don't criticize the military. You don't.
Okay. And she did that. So that's why
she's out. Uh
and then about 22 or 23 days later,
suddenly there's a conflration. Both
sides are accusing each other of of
starting the fight. But that's where we
are. So this could evolve if this is not
stopped now. This could pos potentially
evolve into a proxy conflict between the
US and China possibly.
Yeah, Thailand its military is strong
enough to take Cambodia if they want.
They can affect a regime change in
Cambodia if they want. They that strong
Thailand Cambodia doesn't have a strong
military. So why did Mr. Hunson start
this this entire thing? Maybe to
consolidate his hold in power inside
Cambodia. When you have an external
threat, you can have the people rally
around the flag kind of, you know. Uh so
maybe that's the reason, but this could
evolve into a proxy conflict between the
US and China like what's happening in
Burma, right? In Burma, you have half
the country which is no longer in the
under the control of the Burmese
government and you have the project K
that the Biden regime started the cookie
land for Christ nonsense which is which
has spilled over into Manipur and it's
created a completely abysmal situation
in Manipur. Right? So this could this
could destabilize central uh sorry not
central but Southeast Asia further if
this is not contained. So that's the
situation we have to wait and watch.
Okay, next question. Manka Seeker Biswas
says, "Russia's Africa Corps now
officially under the Kremlin's defense
ministry has replaced the Wagner
mercenary network across Mali, Nijair,
Burkinaaso, embedding itself as a formal
security partner. Does this mark a
durable realignment away from Western
influence and with implications for
terrorism dynamics, resource access in
the international security
architecture?"
Let's go to the map. We'll quickly take
a look at uh
Africa the region that we are talking
about. Let us uh remove this. All right.
Here we are. So we are talking about
these nations in the Sahel region of
Africa
which is also called the coup belt of
Africa.
We're talking about nijair.
We're talking about Mali. We're talking
about Burkina Faso. Um
and these nations are kind of aligned
with Russia. Russia has a significant uh
presence in the Sahel region. It used to
be via the Vagnner group which was a
paramilitary group not officially under
the Kremlin's command but now the
Russian presence is via the Africa core
which is under the Kremlin's direct
command essentially. So it's it's Russia
is now officially involved in this
region as opposed to unofficially the
way it was unofficially involved
earlier. And this comes at a time when
when France is withdrawing or
essentially has withdrawn from Africa. I
think that France has closed down all of
its military bases in the region. Now it
has it has essentially ended more than a
century of colonial presence in the
region. So the French colonizers are
gone and they have been replaced by the
Russians and there's a Chinese presence
also significantly in Africa. So um
Russia and China as we know are working
together to a certain extent. So it's
Russian muscle and Chinese money
essentially which is here and of course
Africa is a tremendously resourcerich
region. Um so of course there there's so
much so many resources to be extracted
over here metals there's uranium there's
oil there's gas there's so much more u
and u the great lakes region also I mean
if you if you look at that the Americans
have a great amount of interest over
here because of the resources in this
region which is the DRC Tanzania Rwanda
Burundi Uganda region Kenya also to some
extent there's another a new scramble
for Africa that's happening right now
and All the big powers are involved in
it. It's all it's just about resources.
It's not about bringing democracy and
freedom and human rights and better
living standards and education and
whatnot to Africa. It's all about
extracting Africa's resources. That's
all what it's about.
Uh so this is a work in progress. The
security architecture whatever you call
it in Africa is realigning right now.
This is not a durable realignment. It's
a work in progress. The Americans have
now designated the Sahil region as the
number one epicenter of terrorism in the
world recently. So apparently Pakistan
is no longer the number one epicenter of
terrorism. It's a Sahil region now.
Really? Whatever. That's what the
Americans say because the Sah region is
slipping out of their grasp. So then you
designate them as terrorists, right?
Obviously makes sense, right? Uh so it's
going to be a contested region now.
Africa,
everybody's going to try and grab
whatever they can. It's all about
resources. So there's going to be
increasing competition in the region.
The Sahel region seems to now be
significantly more and more aligning
with Russia especially the three three
nations we referred to Mali, Nijair and
Bkinaaso. Maybe more nations could come
under that
and uh the Great Lakes region and all
that the Americans are looking at and
the Chinese have a presence there. India
also uh would like to hopefully I I I
would say that India should also be
involved in this not for extracting and
exploiting Africa but you know giving a
win-win situ kind of thing to African
governments.
So yeah it's a work in progress and it's
it's it's good to discuss Africa once in
a while because it's a gigantic part of
the world the largest continent that no
one talks about and it's very important.
So yeah
right what is next question what do we
have
geopolitical dub says how long will
Myanmar
remain in this mess is there any end to
Myanmar's problems okay let's take a
look at the map because uh it's possible
some people don't know where it is so uh
where's the map okay here's the map here
we are talking about Myanmar
So Myanmar hopefully people will know
that it's it's a neighboring country
east of India's far east. That's
Myanmar.
So Myanmar historically has been part of
the Indosphere. Very much part of the
Indosphere. Very Indianized uh culture,
very Indianized civilization. Um it was
the gateway to Surinabumi for us
historically the past 3,000 years when
our traders used to cross the bay of
Bengal in the Andaman Sea and and and
trade with Southeast Asia which we call
Sur Nabumi. So Myanmar was the gateway
to Sur Nabumi for us. Now uh Myanmar
lost lost its sovereignty to the British
in 1926. the treaty of Yandabo, Yandabo
at the end of the first Anglo- Myanmar
war and that is precisely the time when
Manipur also lost its sovereignty to the
British. Uh and slowly the British made
significant inroads into into Burma
and uh they occupied Burma just like
they occupied India.
Okay. And in 1935 there was a vote in
Burma whether to
uh separate from India or not. And they
voted to remain unified with India. But
the British still went ahead and
separated Burma from India. So the
Burmese
leaders wanted to remain unified with
India, united with India but the British
disregarded that vote and they cut Burma
off from India into a separate entity.
Uh and then eventually Burma got its
freedom. Long story. Yeah. Mr. On
General Sanan was the first leader if
I'm not mistaken. Eventually his
daughter becomes the Nobel Prize winner
and so on. Yeah. So he was one of the
freedom fighters for Burma. Uh and then
there's this long long long period where
the Burma is under military rule and
there's no progress, no development,
nothing happening in Burma for the
longest time.
uh that's been the history
uh for the longest time
and the Americans have tried their best
to bring democracy to Burma which means
to make Burma align with the US not with
China. See if India had been a great
power as opposed to China or if Burma
had the option of two great powers India
and China Burma would have always in the
20th century wanted to align with India
but India never gave Burma that offer.
India never rose as a great power that
would that would be a security and
economic guaranter for the other
nations. So Burma had no option. The
Burmese government, the Burmese military
had no option but to align with China.
India was disinterested. India the
Indian government was not even
interested in its own northeast far
east. So how did you expect India to be
interested in Burma? So Burma aligned
with China and in the 21st century
America tried to bring Burma into the
western fold. Barack Obama they they
they had given a Nobel Prize to Onan
Suchi and then there was this agreement
with the Burmese military government
that there'll be some form of democracy
and and so on and Sanansuchi becomes the
the leader of Burma
for a while before she's put back under
house arrest. We know that and uh when
she was the leader of Burma, she cracked
down on the terrorists, Rohingyas and
that's why the Americans started you
know the west suddenly threatened to
revoke her Nobel Prize if that's even
possible.
Now when it comes to Burma when it comes
to the northern part of Burma once again
let's go to the map. Uh you know a lot
of people aren't Burmese there. So the
neighboring parts there are lots of
nagas in Burma which is fine and lots of
cookies cookie the cookies who who live
the chin cookies who live in Burma
they're not Burmese they don't speak the
Burmese language they don't uh practice
Burmese culture and uh they don't really
have any allegiance with Burma they're
just occupying the land they came from u
possibly from the Yunan region of China
only in recent times they occupied parts
of Burma And uh and there are other
ethnic groups also in the northern part
of Burma. And these all all these ethnic
groups are fighting against the Burmese
government. And some of these are
aligning with the US. Some of these are
aligning aligning with with China. And
the effect is that about half of Burma
is under the control of the of the
Burmese government and the Americans
started this new project right Kulan for
Christ project K. and they spilled that
over into Manipur and because of the
open border that we have with between
India and Burma I don't know lacks and
lacks of cookies have squ have have have
entered into Manipur either for from
misoram or whatever and they have
created an absolute mayhem in Manipur.
So Manipur is half of Manipur at least
more than half is under foreign
occupation right now. Yeah kind of
because we have foreign infiltrators
squatting on our territory. So Burma is
in in civil war
and these
these groups who are fighting the
Burmese government, they have an endless
supply of arms and ammunition coming
from somewhere, right? Some of it will
definitely come from China but not all
of it. So the question is where does the
rest of it come from? And that's a
question we'll have to wonder about, I
would say. So that is the mess in
Myanmar. It's a proxy war between the US
and and China,
right? There are there are Chinese
aligned groups. There are US aligned
groups and there are nationalist groups
which are aligned with the government of
Burma
and the US aligned groups are creating
mayhem in Manipur. Okay. Yeah. So that's
the situation. Is there any end to all
of this?
So what should be the desired end state?
The desired end state for Burma is that
Burma should retain its sovereignty. It
should regain control over all of its
territory. And those
groups who are fighting the Burmese
government need need to be brought to
justice. That would be the logical and
correct end state. Right? I mean if you
say that everybody has the right to
democracy and right to declare
independence and they can apply the same
logic to India, right? I mean it doesn't
work like that. U so this happens when a
nation becomes weak. That's when all
these little ethnic groups start
demanding independence and they start
aligning with foreign powers to
destabilize the country. So Burma is you
know we know that there there are this
breaking India forces. Similarly we are
seeing the the the breaking Burma forces
in action right now and it is in our
interest it is in India's interest that
Burma remains unified and hopefully
aligned with India you know. So uh is
there any end to this? Well, as long as
the Americans in China, as long as the
Burmese government isn't strong enough
to put an end to all this separatism and
foreign interference, this will
continue.
Uh so yeah, right now we don't see an
end to it because the foreign powers are
too strong, the US and China, and they
are tearing Burma apart.
Okay. Pranay Paul says with Singapore's
senior minister openly calling for for a
world minus America trade framework in
response to Trump's tariffs is Singapore
breaking from its traditional vasal like
alignment with the US what's the deeper
truth behind such bold statements real
strategic recalibration or economic
posturing and how might this reshape
India Asia's geopolitical balance in the
coming decade okay so Singapore senior
minister
has recently like yesterday or day
before whatever uh called for a trade
framework a world minus America trade
framework in response to the mayhem that
has been unleashed by by the Trump
administration's tariff war on the world
right so prane is asking is Singapore
therefore breaking from its traditional
vasal-like alignment with the US
is it it's a statement
it's a statement it's just words. It's
uh it's an expression of displeasure.
And you know what? You're going too far.
It's it's it's feedback to the master.
A vasal is allowed to criticize
the master.
You can criticize verbally. You can give
your feedback. You can sometimes say it
in the open.
As long as you don't take any actions
that are detrimental to the master's
interests, nothing happens.
That's how it goes.
Um, so it's just words. I don't care.
It's not important as long as there's no
action that goes that that aligns with
those words. So this is an expression of
displeasure. This is a this is a this is
a nation voicing displeasure, which is
just common sense. I mean, what the
Americans are doing, they're tearing
down the economic order of the world.
So it's it's a statement that makes a
lot of sense and
Singapore is in is not in a position to
stand up to the US and it's not going to
h not going to happen. So there is no
real strategic recalibration. There is
this is just words. It's just words.
It's not going to reshape any
geopolitical balance in the coming
decade.
Okay. Amisha says please explain the
origins of water. How did water first
appear on the earth? And how are images
of the Milky Way galaxy taken? Okay,
origins of water and how did water first
appear on the earth? See, water is a
chemical substance. It's made of two
atoms of hydrogen, one atom of oxygen.
Hydrogen is H. So, it's H2O. Hydrogen is
the most abundant element in the
universe. It was formed in the aftermath
of the Big Bang. Hydrogen is an is an
element that has one proton and one
electron. That's it. The simplest atom
that you can have. So it's uh so that's
hydrogen. Then you have oxygen which has
eight protons in its nucleus
and eight electrons that uh go around it
kind of in orbitals. So uh hydrogen was
created in the aftermath of the big bang
in great great quantities abundance of
hydrogen also helium but oxygen wasn't
formed in the aftermath of the big bang.
It wasn't until the first supernovas
occurred in the universe that the
formation of oxygen of of water
happened. So uh oxygen is formed inside
stars as a consequence of fusion nuclear
fusion.
Uh and when a star goes supernova that's
when tremendous amounts of water are
produced very counterintuitively but yes
all the oxygen that's inside the star it
it gets to react with hydrogen and large
quantities of water are formed during
supernova explosions. the combination of
hydrogen and oxygen essentially and
water is one of the most abundant
chemical substances in the universe
right now. Uh you can find signatures of
water everywhere. Uh
there you know vast reservoirs of water
have been discovered in orbit around
quazars. Quazars are active galactic
nuclei that are powered by super massive
black holes. And there's this big
accretion disc, you know, this this I'll
let's put an image of that on the
screen.
What a quazar looks like. So there's
this this big accretion disc that is uh
that's which has infalling matter. Okay,
quazar.
This is what a quazar looks like. A
representation of of a quazar. That's a
tremendous amount of mass and material
and matter that's falling into a black
hole. And that's yeah this essentially
is a galaxy with it with this situation.
Um so there have been quazars that have
been discovered that have huge
reservoirs of water vapor in the
occasion disc that's falling into the
black hole. How much water? Trillions of
times the amount of water we have on the
planet earth.
More than 100 trillion I think 140
trillion times the amount of water in
the oceans of the earth. That's how much
water was discovered around one in the
occlion disc around one quazar. So water
is extremely abundant in the universe.
Okay. So that's the origin of water. It
originated initially
during supernova explosions and then
it's become one of the most common
commonplace substances in the universe.
Now how did water first appear on earth?
So the earth was formed about about 4
and a half billion years ago when our
solar system was formed. Our solar
system was formed out of a protostellar
disc which was a huge cloud of gas and
dusk dust. And that cloud of gas and
dust where did all the ga gas and dust
come from? It came from the debris of of
supernova explosions. So there were
previous stars that went supernova and
died and all the gas and dust and
whatever else debris was left over. It
eventually once again coalesed together
and formed a new solar system. So our
star is a our sun, the sun that that
gives us life. It's a reborn star. It's
maybe a sec second or third generation
star. Okay? And it's had ancestors who
lived and died.
So about 4 and a half billion years ago,
the solar system starts forming as a
protostellar disc. Let me show you what
a protoella disc looks like.
Let's put that on the screen.
Okay,
this is what a protoellar disc looks
like. This is an actual image,
protolanetary disc, protostellar disc,
whatever you want to call it. So when
when the gas starts combining once again
starts coming together because of
self-gravitation
it starts spinning around a center
that's just how it goes because of
Newtonian physics very simple and at the
center eventually a lot of gas combines
together and it ignites nuclear fusion
and that's the birth of a new star and
that's how the sun was born and
eventually you had other planets also
that formed around the sun along the
same disc right in the in the same
the same plane as the original
protostellar disc. So, uh that's how the
solar system was formed. So, there's a
lot of substances, lot of stuff that was
left over from previous stars, right?
And as we know, supernovas give rise
give birth to water. And obviously, you
had previous stars that lived there with
possibly planetary systems of their own.
So, they would have had water in those
planets as well.
So a lot of the water that became part
of the solar system was water that was
left over from the previous solar
systems that had existed before the
stars went supernova.
So the earth forms about 4 and a half
billion years ago. It's a hellish world
nothing like what we see and experience
today. It's a huge hot not huge similar
sized thing planet but it's extremely
hot. It's full of lava and magma is
bubbling away. The atmosphere is toxic
to us living on the earth today. Very
different atmosphere. And there was this
period called the Hadian period in the
early solar systems history. A period of
intense bombardment bombardment by
asteroids and fragments and of rock and
whatnot. And it is believed that these
asteroids and comets and fragments of
rocks rock and all that these objects
they all had water on them and that's
how this water was became you know it it
it reached earth through this
bombardment by asteroids and and rocks
and all that. So it is believed that a
large amount of the water that exists on
earth today it it came on the planet
through through these collisions with
all the debris that existed in the solar
system in the initial in the early uh
part of the solar systems history. So
that's how water appeared on earth
through collisions and then there was
another gigantic collision which is
believed to have happened which gave
rise to the moon. Even that collision
with a smaller planet which is now part
of the earth. Even that collision may
have brought water to the earth. So
that's how water appeared on earth. It's
a long process. It happened through very
violent activity. That's the uh most
likely explanation that we have thus
far. How are images of the Milky Way
taken? U you take them with cameras and
you expose the camera in a very dark
part of the see today if you live in
cities there's a lot of light pollution.
You can hardly see the sky. So you to go
to some remote area where there's
complete darkness hopefully and then you
take long exposures at night and you
will see some part of the Milky Way. Now
you cannot take a proper image of the
Milky Way from outside because we are
inside the Milky Way. Our solar system
is is is in one of the arms of the Milky
way. The Milky Way is most likely a
spiral galaxy. So you take pictures like
that and you So let me show you some
pictures. What do these pictures look
like once again? Uh Milky Way picture,
right? Milky Way picture.
So when when you get images like this of
the Milky Way, these are artistic
representations.
This is an art this is an artist's
imagination of what what the Milky Way
looks like. We don't really know what it
looks like from from outside. We have no
way of going outside the Milky Way and
taking pictures like these. So these are
artistic representations. These are
actual images of the Milky Way from
inside the Milky Way. So we can only
imagine what the Milky Way structure is
like based on whatever data we have. So
this is what it looks like when we take
images from inside the Milky Way from
from our our own planet.
Uh that's what it looks like. And if you
if you actually
experience this, if you go to a dark
part of the planet where there's real
good darkness and if you look out at the
sky and you see the real Milky Way, it's
it's an all inspiring sight. It looks
like it's a cloud. So many stars. I
remember when I was a little kid, the
first time I saw that, I was aruck. Look
at the number of stars we have out
there. So yeah, that's how it is. So you
have to take images in in a in a part of
the planet where there's no light
pollution and that's how we do that's
how we do it and you take multiple
exposures and you stitch them together
and that's how you get a better image.
All right. Okay. Amisha has another
question. What why was it a taboo for
Hindus to cross the sea? How did this
practice originate in Indian society?
And what's the difference between 80 BC
BCE? It's really confusing. Okay, the
taboo for crossing for Hindus to cross
the sea.
First of all, let's look at some actual
history.
Uh we know that Southeast Asia became
Indianized over thousands of years,
right? We called Southeast Asia
Sarabumi.
Uh let's go to the map and we'll put the
map on the screen. One second. Give me a
second.
Okay,
so here's the map. We're looking at
India from Southeast Asia's perspective.
Uh we have Indonesia,
uh Yawadwep and Sumatra, Java and
Sumatra. And uh we have the Philippines
which were called Maharlic. Then we have
Thailand, Cambodia, Vietnam, Myanmar,
all of that. All of this taken together
is uh Southeast Asia. Now, Indian
traders were trading with Sarabumi,
which is Southeast Asia for at least
3,000 years before today. And they did
not uh go to Southeast Asia via land.
They used to cross the Bay of Bengal,
cross the Andaman Sea and trade with
Southeast Asia. U one of the first
Indianized kingdoms emerged in southern
Vietnam. It was called Funan. And uh
there was a and the king of the first
king of Funan was an Indian trader
called Condinhia
and his queen was a local lady her name
was Queen S I believe. Uh so these were
traders from Kolinga from Odisha who
used to travel across the sea 3,000 plus
years ago and for thousands of years
they traded with this region and they
totally slowly gradually Indianized this
this region without any force whatsoever
without any coercion whatsoever.
So obviously we had ships flying the Bay
of Bengal, what is now called the Bay of
Bengal. It should be called the Sea of
Kolinga. Actually then we also know that
we have had Indians living in Eastern
Africa for thousands of years. If you
look at the culture of Southeast Asia,
all the way to Mozambique, all the way
to Tanzania etc. You will see Indian
influence everywhere in the in the kind
of clothing they wear, the kind of
cuisine they have, even in their facial
features. You will see it especially in
Somalia, Ethiopia
etc.
So Indians obviously they did not walk
into Africa. They crossed the sea. When
Vasco Dagama first reached Africa after
crossing the Cape of Good Hope, they was
astonished to see ships that were like
three four times the size of his ship
and they were commanded by Indians. And
it's Indians who sadly unwittingly
brought Fasco Dama to India. Right? So
Indians were crossing the ocean all the
time. If you look, if you read the riga,
it speaks about ships that have 100 or
ships equipped with 100 oes.
2,000 years ago, the Romans had ships
called galleys, Roman galleys. These
ships had 500 oes. Let me show you.
Roman galleys.
Uh, not glets, galleys. GS. There we
are. Roman galley. So, these were
military ships. They were designed for
ramming other ships. And these ships
would typically have 50 or 25 on each
side. These were the elite warships of
the Roman era, the Roman warships, 50 BC
or whatever. And the guys who would be
manning operating the os were generally
sadly slaves.
Okay. So these were the elite warships
of the Roman era. The rigidic era you
had you had ships with twice the number
of oes that the Romans used.
So these were not obvious these were
obviously not river fairing ships. These
were seafaring ships. They went out on
the samudra. The rivida was was written
closer to 6,000 BC than to 1500 BC.
So we've always had this practice of
crossing the sea. We have we were the
first maritime civilization of all. I
can give you so many more examples of
Indians crossing the sea. But we are
told I mean our textbooks tell us that
there was some taboo that Indians could
not cross the sea. Mr. Gandhi, Mr. Moas
Gandhi writes about this that uh your
dharma will become brushed or whatever
if you cross the sea. So how so assuming
it's true, how did it originate in
India? I suspect that if it is true that
it originated in the past 10,000 years
when India came under foreign occupation
and it was not a good idea for any young
man to leave his family and go somewhere
else in search of adventure or or
whatever you were supposed to stay at
home and defend your home and if you
left your home and cross the sea went
far away then you were no longer a
dharmic person. I suspect that's what
must have happened because of the past
1,000 years of foreign occupation. first
Turk occupation and then European
occupation. So maybe that's why we got
this. So when when your society is under
foreign occupation and it's it's no
longer able to uh operate the way it
naturally operates, then all kinds of
defects and deficiencies creep into so
into your society. And this is one of
those examples. There are obviously
more. So yeah, that's that's most likely
what happened.
Okay. Sharma 108X says, "What exactly
was S in the context of the Rigveda and
how was it used? Did psychedelics play a
role in ancient Indian spirituality?"
So the riga makes lots of references to
something called s.
When we say s, we also have somar,
right? Somar. It's one of the days of
the week. Raviar, Shanear, Somar,
Mangalwar and so on. Somar is is Monday.
Monday. M O N D A Y. Monday. What is M O
N? Moon.
In French, it's li. L U N D I. The word
for for moon in French is lun. L U N E.
Sumoir, Monday, learn. Exactly the same
meaning, the day of the moon. So s means
moon historically for us. But in the
original context, the rigidic context,
it meant a certain plant.
And the rigid extols the the the virtues
of soma s ras. So it was a plant that
our ancestors
held in extremely high regard. So the
stalks of the plant were harvested and
they were pressed and a juice was
extracted which was called saras. And
this was consumed by warriors before
battle. It gave them tremendous stamina
and strength and vigor.
Lord Indra was a great uh drinker of
sas.
So the rigida has so many references,
lots and lots of references to s and and
the benefits of drinking s.
So it's clearly some it clearly was an
actual plant. Now today we don't know
what that plant is. is I mean it's it's
kind of a mystery. They've kind of lost
touch with what s used to be. So um and
then this what's interesting is that the
Persians also have soma.
So we do yagnas. The Persians they do
what they call yajna yashnas. It's the
same thing but slightly different
pronunciation. The Persian language the
old Persian language was very similar to
Sanskrit. It was an offshoot of
Sanskrit. It was an upper branch
descendant of Sanskrit. So they used to
call it yasna and sa becomes her in the
Persian language. So they used to so our
soma became their homer homer and the
Persians the Zoroastrians when they when
they came to India running from the
Arabic invaders they brought Homer with
them and that happened to be the Ephedra
plant. Ephedra let me let's let's
quickly Google that.
Uh Ephedra Excuse me.
So the ephedra plant looks like this.
Now I'm not claiming that this is the
this is guaranteed to be soma, but this
is what the ephedra plant looks like.
It's a stimulant. Okay. Um
this is what it looks like. It it it
grows. Where does it grow? Let's let's
find out where it grows. Ephedra is a
plant. Where does it grow? Does it do we
have Okay, so this is where it grows.
So it is believed that uh the rigidic
original area was northern western
India. So yeah it makes sense and of
course Porschia also there. So uh what's
the use of ephedra human use? Ephedra
medicine nandaral shanidar crave kurasan
ephedra pololland all that uh ephedrine
ephedrine is a is a controlled substance
I believe it's a stimulant central
nervous system stimulant and uh
uh I think athletes are banned from
taking it because it gives you yeah it's
a performance-enhancing drug in exercise
and sports it can increase heart rate
blood pressure cardiac contractility and
act as a psycho stimulant, right?
And it's often used in combination with
caffeine
for performance enhancing purposes and
the food. So there are regulations and
all and I think athletes if they are
found with ephedra in the system, I
think you you are banned or whatever and
your medals will be revoked if you are
found with ephedra in your system.
So this is a candidate I would say. I'm
not claiming that this is the soma
itself but it's I think a strong
candidate for being possibly the soma of
the rigida. So when the paris do their
yasnas they use ephedra as soma and for
us I'm not sure what we use.
Yeah. Um so that's what soma was. It was
this great fantastic plant whose rust
whose whose juice would be consumed
consumed and that would give you
tremendous uh performance enhancement
and you would win in battle. That's what
soma was and it's kind of lost in
history. Some people say it is the
psilocybin mushroom. I don't think
that's the case. The psilocybin mushroom
has very strong hallucinogenic
properties. It get sends you into some
kind of weird mental state where you see
unicorns and whatnot. rainbows and
whatnot I believe. Okay. I I I believe
it's pretty common in India. The
psilocybin mushroom. Um so but it's not
a performance-enhancing substance. It
won't guarantee b victory in battle. It
may end end up getting you killed in
battle if you are seeing things that
aren't there. Right? So I don't think
psy is is the is the answer to the
mystery. It's possibly ephedra.
We'll have to see. So I'm not sure what
fedra is called in India. Uh we can find
it out later. Uh did psychedelics play a
role in Indian uh ancient Indian
spirituality. Well, psychedelics have
been a part of Indian culture. Bhang is
obviously what is bhang? It's it's a
marijuana, right? Maruana. Marijuana is
is ganja. It's it's a it's a it's a herb
that can be ingested. Uh it can be eaten
or it can be smoked.
And it's uh sap or whatever is is
converted into this bhang balls or
whatever and people drink that with milk
or whatever during holi
um and it's never been taboo. It's not
something that is something you should
do all the time but on special occasions
on holidays or festivals or whatever on
certain on certain festivals it's
consumed. One of the festivals obviously
is holi when people drink bang. I've
never had it so I have no idea what it
is like but I've heard very interesting
stories about bang and another festival
is Shivatri where people smoke some
people some people smoke ganja a couple
of puffs or whatever or whatever and
there are certain sadhus in India who
smoke copious amounts of ganja and whatn
not so it's it's part of our culture
it's been there for thousands of year
years
and uh
and I'm not sure if it's a good thing or
a bad thing Sure, it's not a bad thing
if you do it once or twice a year,
right? As a ritual thing. Of course, I
suppose these substances will have
addictive properties and obviously if if
somebody consumes them or smokes them
regularly, you're going to have bad
health effects. But if you do it once or
twice a year, no one cares. Um, and I'm
sure Indians were in in old ancient
times were not encouraged to do this all
the time. It was something you did for
ritual purposes, religious purposes,
once or twice a years or once or twice a
year. So yeah, that's the kind of thing
it we had historically.
Sharma 108x says the subjugated rivals
of the Aztecs played a crucial role in
the conquest of the Aztec Empire by
helping the Espanos, the Spanish
concistadors,
right? Hernand Cortez. Hernan Cortez was
the Spanish barbarian
who destroyed the Aztec Empire in the
year 1521.
Hernan Cortez
and the other one the other barbarian
was Franchesco Pidaro who destroyed the
Inca Empire in southern America.
Uh long story I've I've Yeah. So So the
subjugated rivals of the Aztecs played a
crucial role in the conquest of the
Aztec Empire by helping the Spanish.
Could you discuss why they chose to side
with the Spanish and what happened to
them after the Spanish gained control of
all of Mexico, Mexico? So, let's once
again go to the map and we're going to
take a look at that part of the world
for a change.
So, we're talking about Central America
here, Mexico City.
It was called Tenok Titlan during the
the days of the Triple Alliance.
So I'm not sure where the the great lake
is. But this city was founded as an
island city inside a lake. I think the
lake has been wiped out. It's been
reclaimed. All the land has been
reclaimed and there's nothing of the
lake left now. So uh this is where it
all happened. So there was something
called the Aztec triple triple alliance.
Okay, which was which is which everyone
calls the Aztec Empire. It was a
political and military entity which was
founded in in the 1400s. The first half
of the 1400s by three city states. The
first and most powerful was Tenotitlan
which is Mexico City itself. Then there
was something called Texoko and there
was Takopan.
So these three city states they came
together combined their resources and
created a triple alliance which everyone
calls the Aztec Empire. Now the most
powerful obviously was Tenokitlan and
that that's the and that Tenuktitlan
controlled the entire uh Azak Empire. So
this was an alliance
and it was
okay. Now let's remove the map. Yep. So
this alliance was it was crucial in the
in the foundation the establishment of
the empire and the expansion of the
empire. So once you pull the resources
of three entities, three geopolitical
entities together, then it becomes a
much more powerful entity and this
alliance allowed this empire to dominate
this entire region, the valley of Mexico
and they were able to that thereby they
were able to control and subjugate
various other uh political entities in
the region and they conquered many other
territories in what's called Miso
America which is essentially Central
America. America. So there were many
other small um city states or whatever
small kingdoms that were absorbed,
subjugated and absorbed and made part of
the Aztec Empire.
So they were all under
the dominance of essentially the main
entity which was based out of Mexico
City. So in the 1520s 1520 1521 this guy
Hernand Cortez comes to this region.
Okay. He crosses see he crosses the
ocean from Spain the Atlantic Ocean and
he reaches Mexico and he he he's out for
glory obviously all these concistadors
they were hidalos or they were nobodyies
and they wanted to make a name for
themselves and they wanted great riches
and glory they sought adventure and they
sought gold
and uh it all started obviously in with
uh with Christopher Columbus discovering
what he thought was India but whatever
So in 1521, Khan Cortez comes here with
a bunch of soldiers and these other
kingdoms that had been defeated and
incorporated into the Aztec Empire. They
decided that you know what these
foreigners, let's ally with them and
let's bring the Aztec Empire down.
So that's what they did. So, Hernand
Cortez and his uh army they got a huge
number of allies by exploiting the the
hidden divisions in the empire and then
they made their move on Tokitlan which
is now called Mexico City
and they would still not have won but
something happened. What was that
something? It was smallox.
The Europeans brought small pox to the
region and while they were fighting the
the Aztec Empire and they were fighting
for Mexico City, half of the people of
Mexico City were dying of smallpox and
that's what contributed to the eventual
destruction of the Azik Empire and the
victory of the Spanish and the Spanish
never left.
So what happened to the other uh the
subjugated rivals of the Aztecs? They
were all destroyed one by one. They were
all
Yeah. What happened happened you know
the Spanish even today the the language
spoken in Mexico is Spanish. The
religion in in Mexico is is the Catholic
version of Christianity which is brought
by the Spanish and the churches in
Mexico are church are are built on top
of destroyed temples Mexican temples. So
the fate of the Aztecs was shared by
everybody else including the rivals.
Everybody suffered cultural endemic
genocide. That's what happened. So
that's something you see over and over
again in the history of colonization in
the past 500 years. Whether it is in the
Americas, whether it is in Asia,
wherever else, whether it's Africa,
the the invaders, the colonizers, they
exploit divisions between the natives
and they eventually end up destroying
everything. So the natives who who
initially think that you know let's ally
with the foreigners they have just come
from somewhere else and they'll they'll
leave what happens is they never leave
and even if you allied with them they
will destroy you as well. So that's
something that's happened over and over
again. That's a that's a pattern that
repeats itself in the uh story of
colonization in the past 500 or so
years.
Okay. Saturn 88 says very interesting
question very interesting question. Is
there an infinite number of souls or
atmas in the universe? For example,
there were maybe two or three billion
humans a few decades ago to today the
population is 8.1 billion. Where are all
these new souls coming from? So it is
said that there are more people alive
today on the planet
than people who have ever died. So if
you take all the people who have died in
human history together and you add up
the numbers that number is less than the
number of people alive today
that raises a profound theological
question.
Where are all these? So assuming that
all human beings have a soul atma
and assuming that there is reincarnation
then where are all these extra souls
coming from?
That's that's a very profound question
and I'm not the right person person to
answer this question but I would like to
ask this question of you my viewers
maybe some of you understand this better
than me what's the answer to this
question see I am a scientist that's my
background
and I am not an expert in all these
things I have the deepest of respect and
re reverance for our culture but I don't
know the answer to this question.
We have more people alive today than
have ever died before. So where have all
the extra atmas, the souls come from?
Assuming that souls exist and each human
being has one unique soul. So where have
all these souls come from? If you ask
this question to somebody who is a
follower of an Abrahamic religion,
they'll just say God created these
souls. Maybe God is in the process of
creating extra souls. That answers the
question. But when it comes to the
dharmic religions, there are laws of
nature including laws that that that
govern the spiritual invisible world,
the the non-physical world, right? I
mean there are non-physical objects that
like the atma etc in our in our
philosophy, philosophical schools of
thought and in our culture. But those
two are governed by laws.
They things aren't aren't arbitrary.
There are laws that govern the universe
even even the nonphysical aspects of the
universe according to our culture and
civilization.
So how does that account for the extra
souls that exist today that have we've
never had these many souls during the
rigidic phase of our history? How many
people existed in in India in the
subcontinent?
I would guess less than a million
perhaps.
And the total population of the world at
the time would have been perhaps just a
few millions, maybe 5 million or
something. But today you have 8.1
billion. Where did all these extra souls
come from? That's a very profound
theological question.
So I would like I I don't have the
answer to it.
So, it's it's fascinating, but I'm sure
there should be some kind of u logical
answer to this. So, so let me know what
you guys think maybe in the comments
below once this live stream is over
because I would like to know the answer
to this question. I don't have the
answer to this question. Fascinating.
Okay.
Geopolitical Dub says, "Do we need
expensive Apache helicopters in today's
warfare?" So look the question you to
ask yourself first of all is that do we
have alternatives
the answer is maybe yes we have the LCH
prachund helicopter
which is an indigenous helicopter it's
an attack helicopter which is different
from the Apache so the LCH prachund
helicopter is designed for extreme high
alitude combat Himalayan combat so it
it's something that can give us a
tremendous edge over China in any future
hypothetical hypothetical future
conflict.
So, it's designed to operate even in
Siain, even in the highest parts of the
Himalayas, etc., where the Apache simply
can't operate. Impossible. The Apache
helicopter has a more powerful engine
from what I hear. And it it is a heavier
helicopter. It can carry a much heavier
payload, which means more weapons, more
missiles, more whatever else. And it is
more it is it is an armored kind of
helicopter. So it can take hits. You
shoot at it, it'll be fine.
So it's different from the LCH Prand.
The LCH is not that heavily armored. It
doesn't have as powerful of an engine as
the Apache helicopter, and it can't
carry as many armaments, let's say, as
the Apache.
But look, if this is the only helicopter
you have, fine. Make lots of those. Make
2,000 of those, then it's fine. you
you'll be fine. Uh now price-wise, I
think the Apache helicopter is priced
around $100 million per piece
and the Pchand is priced about half of
that, 50 million. So the Apache is
obviously more expensive, but it's it's
a very highly battle tested helicopter.
The Apache has seen a lot of action. The
Prchand hasn't seen action thus far. I'm
not saying it means that it's a bad
helicopter. I'm just saying it's not
tested in battle thus far. The Apache is
very battle tested. It's been around for
a very long time. So based on these
parameters that we have on both sides, I
think the government of India or the
Indian armed forces need to decide what
the uh uh how they're going to go about
doing things. Do they need a bunch of
Apaches and a bunch of uh Peran
helicopters or do they want more Apaches
and less preach or just a handful of
Apaches and a whole bunch of Pchends? So
that's something the armed forces are
best equipped to decide.
I think I think we should go indigenous
more. So we already have a bunch of
Apache helicopters. Good. Keep those and
use those. But we should
uh get we should induct way more of the
indigenous helicopter. Um and obviously
we should keep on developing the
indigenous helicopter make more versions
of that you know maybe a heavier more
more armored and more powerful version
of the Pchan maybe we can we can
certainly do that we can adapt it you
know so yeah I think that's the
direction in which we should go
right
um okay
uh Latangi Suresh says the generation
before you before me
used to see encyclopedias for answers
and also books for answers. You in your
generation which is me even now use
Google instead of perplexity or chat
jpity for answers. Don't assume things
sir. You don't know what I what I use. I
use everything. But anyhow you you're
generalizing. Okay. So Gen X my
generation is Gen X the last great
generation.
So yeah Gen X uses Google instead of
Perplexity or Chart GPD for answers. And
you use Google or any search engine and
that made the word Google as a term for
finding out new things. Google this,
Google that. Yeah. Right now our
generation Gen Z searches chat GPD for
things the way you search for things in
Google. Okay. So what will the future
generations that is Gen Alpha etc do for
the same? if they want to search for
something will they just think an AI
would provide answers through Neuralink
or agentic AI or would they be in such a
state as to not know anything as they
would be aware of all things that happen
in the whole world
so look I'll tell you what as a kid I
had no no Google
I used to read books I I I read a
tremendous amount of books also not
really encyclopedias I was not a big fan
of encyclopedias but I read a lot of
books
tremendous amount of books. Then go then
something called the internet arrived in
India in the late 1990s when I was in
university.
Okay. And the internet that we had in
India in the late '90s 97 98 99 it was
it was ridiculously overpriced and
ridiculously slow extremely frustrating.
Then the 2000s you got better and better
internet over time. For a time we had
something called cyber cafes in India.
So if you wanted to access the internet
you had to go to a cyber cafe and pay
something per hour and you had a slowish
connection. Yeah that's what you used to
have. Then eventually you started
getting you know all these service
providers emerged so that you could have
internet in your home and you have Wi-Fi
and so on. Uh so I've always been an
early adopter of all technologies. I am
very comfortable with technology. I
always keep learning new things. Uh so I
have been in the books phase, the the
encyclopedias phase, I have been in the
Google phase, now we in the AI phase. I
use everything. Uh
but today what you but the problem is
that you know Google Google isn't an
answer engine. Google is is a search
engine. Google doesn't give you answers.
Google gives you links to websites that
may possibly have answers and those
websites aren't necessarily reliable.
And that's what people don't understand.
They think Google told us this so it's
true. It's not necessarily true. People
don't understand that that you have to
fact check everything. But people are
too lazy or just not literate enough to
understand that. And today you have all
these uh all these LLMs chat GPT and
perplexity and whatnot. Even those
aren't necessarily going to give you the
right answers. You still have to fact
check everything. But people don't
understand that.
That's it. I'm done. I got the answer.
at JPT isn't necessarily going to give
you the right answer but people don't
get it anyhow that's that's not what
he's asking you here Suresh so uh yeah
so today Gen Z it asks chat JPD for
everything he doesn't even bother to do
Google right you don't do a Google
search anymore you just ask chat GPD
what is the truth or you ask Grock if
you're on Twitter hey Grock is it true
or perplexity so what will future
generations do genpha or whatever what
AI will evolve maybe everybody will have
a chip in the bra when the brain which
is ridiculous but who knows who knows
that would be terrible but yeah maybe or
maybe you won't even need a chip maybe
you will find there'll be you know
direct to brain wis knows anything's
possible when it comes to technology so
maybe in 10 years today whatever we do
will be regarded as very primitive today
you go to your phone and you you know
ask chat tpd whatever you want in 10
years time maybe that will be regarded
as a very primitive way of interacting
with AI I'm not sure what direction it
will go in. I imagine eventually you
will have Wi-Fi that will interface
directly with your brain with your mind
and you won't need to use fingers to
type or whatever or or thumbs to type on
on the small screens. Maybe you'll be
able to query the AI directly from your
mind. You know, just think and you
you're querying it. Or maybe you can
close your eye and you'll see the screen
and you can just think whatever you want
type. Maybe that will happen. you know
it sounds like science fiction today but
you know what's happening right now 10
years ago was science fiction AI
um yeah so the future is out there all
possibilities are open and I don't know
what exactly will be the way people use
AI but it will be but whatever it will
be they will regard what we are doing
today as super primitive that's what's
going to happen
okay sun moon 0877 says, "After the
Epstein case, I've come to the
conclusion that all the anti-India
influences, politicians, actors have
been 1,000% honey.
The question, why doesn't India use this
honey trapped method method towards the
US or China or even Bangladesh since it
works like a charm and costs less?"
Okay, the Epstein case. Yeah, Epstein is
this this this person who was in charge
of who was running this operation with
his girlfriend Julain Maxwell who's in
prison now and there have been
accusations of pedophilia and god knows
what other hor horrific things and
apparently there's a list of people who
have been Epstein clients and the list
is apparently doesn't exist that's what
Trump says and of course there are lots
of pictures and videos of Trump with
Epstein and Julian Maxwell on the
internet So obviously he was a at least
a friend of epste
and what is believed is that epste was
running this disgusting operation honey
people uh taking them to his island and
doing all kinds of god knows what
horrific things there and apparently
these were very powerful very rich
people who all were clients of epste and
whatever disgusting things that they did
all of that apparently
it is believed by some was videotaped
all of that was taped and now epste and
whoever controls epste has all the
evidence you need to destroy a person.
Now let's say in the future that person
becomes the president of so- and so
country then you can control the entire
country because you have this leverage
over that person and that's how whoever
was behind the Epstein operation they
essentially control a large part of the
world through blackmail. So that's the
that's what is believed by some people.
I'm not saying it's true or it's untrue.
I'm saying we don't have evidence but
yeah it makes sense if it were to be
true. Right? So that's the honey trap
method. That's a black blackmail method.
That's blackmail. Pure blackmail. Honey
trap means you you have some person of
interest and you want that person to
dulge whatever secrets or information
they have or and act as your agent in
your spy. Then you then you honey trap
the person means you you introduce the
person accidentally to your agent who is
a female or a male depending on the
gender of the person of your of your
target. And then you have them get into
a romantic relationship, maybe get
married or maybe just have an affair or
whatever. then you can control that
person. That's that's the classic trap
that that goes back to the days of
Vishnu Gupta Tanaka those we had those
ladies called Vishkanyas and whatnot. So
it's it's the one of the oldest tricks
in the book when it comes to these uh
you know influence operations and and
whatnot and and it's not just anti-India
influencers and politicians and actors
who have could possibly be
uninterrupted. Can you think of an
anti-India influencer who has a foreign
spouse? I I'm not taking anyone's name
up. Can you think of anybody? Maybe
that's foreign that foreign spouse is is
a reward or a honey trap for services
rendered. Can you think of any
any top American
Can you think of any top American
tech company founder who has a Chinese
spouse, Chinese origin spouse? Can you
think of somebody? I'm once again not
taking names. So the Chinese have been
very good at doing this honey trapping
Americans long term. But what about
India? I think India is way behind on
all these things. So yeah, I I suppose I
mean the the suggestion you're giving is
a good suggestion. We should also
uh utilize such means. Why not? What's
wrong with that? No one's being forced
into anything. But if somebody wants to
volunteer as part of a intelligence
operation to be the honey trap then why
not let it let it be right. So yeah I
think yeah you make a good good point
over here.
Okay Sunmoon0877 once again says why
don't Indians fight against racism and
discrimination in countries like the US,
Canada, Ireland etc. How in your tips uh
to fight against it? Look, first of all,
I'll tell you what. All countries have
some amount of racism. Okay? Every every
culture, every country believes that
they are better than others. And there's
there's going to be and and there are
some nations they don't like and there's
going to be some amount of racism in
every country. Every single country on
the planet, it's it's just a natural
thing. Now, what are the tips to fight
against racism? Uh well, if you're an
Indian and you are in a foreign country,
let's say in the US, Canada, Ireland,
wherever, and you face racism,
well, I would say
if you're a tourist and you're there
for, let's say, a few days and you face
some kind of racism, maybe you go to a
restaurant and somebody treats you badly
because of your nationality or the color
of your skin or whatever, I would say
there's no point making a big fuss of
fuss about it and fighting and doing all
that. Just remove yourself from the
situation and go to a better place.
That's what I would say. There's no
point if you're if you're there for like
3 days, 5 days, 1 week, whatever.
There's no point fighting everybody or
or wherever you face this. Just remove
yourself from that place and go
somewhere else. There are plenty of
better establishments, better
restaurants, better whatever where you
will be treated like the way you should
be.
So, if you are a short-term visitor,
don't fight anybody. just just accept
the fact that there's going to be racism
in every country and there's no point
fighting it. But if you are a resident
or a citizen, if you are a Indian origin
US citizen or or whatever citizen and
you face racism, then you can't just,
you know, walk away from it. You've got
to fight it. So how do you fight it? is
they if I'm sure every country has
certain laws that that make it illegal
to discriminate against someone on the
basis of their n of their ethnic origin
or color of the skin or religion or
whatever and if somebody is doing that
then you can pro probably prosecute them
under the laws of the country. So that's
what you can do. U so yeah take take
advantage of the country's laws to
ensure that you are not a you don't
become a victim of racism. And one more
thing I would say to Indian travelers
these days you we see a lot of racism
and hate against Indians on social media
and they give examples of Indians
behaving badly in western countries and
you know what there is some truth to
that
Indians who who become residents and
citizens of foreign countries they
assimilate very well and they behave
very well they are super low abiding
they never create a nuisance or
whatever. But Indian tourists who go on
short-term trips 5 days, 1 week, 2
weeks, whatever to various countries,
they create a very bad image of the
country through their behavior.
Today anybody can travel. Traveling is
cheap. So everybody just travels and you
know they create a nuisance. Indians
they are super loud. They don't realize
that in other countries there's the
there isn't a culture of being loud. You
go to any Indian restaurant, there's
loud music blaring everywhere. Okay?
Even in the most expensive restaurants
in big cities, you you go there, you'll
find loud music blaring, which is why
everybody is forced to shout. So Indians
have this habit of shouting. Now when
you go abroad, people don't shout there.
People like silent. People like a quiet
atmosphere. But Indians will be like
yelling and shouting and they don't even
realize that they they're you know
creating a nuisance for everybody. Then
Indians like to litter everywhere. So
Indians through their behavior
create a bad impression of India. Then
they will haggle with everybody try to
bargain. See in other countries when you
have a price listed on on some item you
have to pay the the the listed price.
You don't bargain with them. But Indians
believe that you can bargain with
everybody and they try to bring the
prices down. You know Bali is a Hindu
place but I've heard that the Balindians
people are tired of Indians because of
Indian behavior. So there's a lot that
Indians do to create this negative image
of India. So I would say that Indians
need to first culturally sensitize
themselves that if I'm going to so and
so country, what are the norms there?
What is expected and what is not
expected of you? Right? What what are
the things you are you can do? What are
the things you should not do? But
Indians don't bother to do that. And
that's the problem. That's what creates
these the opportunity for racists to
then say that India India Indians are
bad and Indians should be discriminated
against and all that. So you know
Indians also need to understand that
when you travel abroad please behave
yourselves behave yourselves like
civilized human beings. You're not in
your country now. You are in a foreign
country. Don't disrespect your hosts or
do anything to make your hosts
uncomfortable. You are now ambassadors
of your nation and behave yourselves in
that manner.
Okay.
Uh okay. A couple of questions here.
Mrianka Biswas and geopolitical Dubai.
Uh why is France recognizing Palestine?
Why do France and the EU countries seem
to be unhappy with Benjamin Netanyahu?
And France has become the first G7
nation to formally recognize the state
of Palestine, announcing the move ahead
of the UN General Assembly in September
with strong international backlash from
the US and Israel. Meanwhile, India has
taken a firm position urging an
immediate ceasefire in Gaza as thousands
of children continue to die daily.
Really, I'm not sure about that. But
anyhow, uh and India has called for uh
humanitarian corridors. Given this
backdrop, do you how do you see Prime
Minister Netanyahu responding
politically and diplomatically in the
coming months, especially as global
momentum shifts towards Palestinian
statethood and ending the war in Gaza?
Okay,
look, there's never been a Palestinian
state. There's never been a country
called Palestine. Okay, you can
retrospectively put names on maps and
all, but there's never been a country
called Palestine. First of all,
understand that. Now, secondly, this
claim that thousands of children are
dying daily. I'm not sure about that. I
know that ever since the war started in
the aftermath of the horrific Hamas
terror attack on Israel and Israeli
Israel justifiably responded by pounding
Gaza and trying to take to to take out
the Hamas terrorists. So, ever since the
war started, I'm sure there have been
lots of deaths in Gaza. Well,
see the so the question is first of all
about France, right? Why? What is France
up to? What is Mu Makon doing formally
recognizing the state of Palestine? And
I think the justification is that
there's been this war that's been going
on for too long and Israel has not
implemented a two-state solution and all
that.
Look, Israel did try its best to
implement a two-state solution. By the
way, they gave the people of Gaza
autonomy, didn't they?
They allowed the people of Gaza to hold
elections and to vote for a government
and for that government to then control
and run Gaza. Right? Israel did that.
Israel gave autonomy to Gaza. And who
did the people of Gaza elect?
They elected Hamas.
And Hamas has been out there trying to
do what it does. It's a terrorist
organization. So, Israel did try its
best to implement a two-state solution.
It did didn't work out. Now, what do you
expect Israel to do? Yeah. Um, and so I
think that's what France is doing. I'm
not sure. I think France is showing off
its its uh uh autonomy,
it it's quasi sovereignty when it comes
to being in the EU and and and NATO.
that despite us being a part of EU and a
part of NATO, we are still quasi
sovereign, right? That sort of thing. So
maybe that's what they that's what Mimo
is up to. Uh obviously there's going to
be strong backlash from the US and from
Israel. I saw a tweet from Prime
Minister Netanyahu um strongly I think
condemning or whatever what uh President
Mron has done recognition of the state
of Palestine. So look, India doesn't
recogni, as far as I know, India doesn't
recognize a Palestinian state. India has
taken a firm position urging an a
ceasefire in Gaza, which makes sense.
Yes, I don't know about thousands of
children dying daily. I don't believe
it. Uh and India has called for
humanitar humanitarian corridors. Yes,
there should be humanitarian corridors.
So how do I see Prime Minister Netanyahu
responding politically and
diplomatically in the coming months? Uh,
is there a global momentum towards
Palestinian statethood? I don't think
so. There certainly is a global demand
for ending the war in Gaza.
So, what will Mr. Netanyahu do?
Uh, well, Mr. Netanyahu has not been
able to achieve his objectives when it
comes to Iran.
He's not been able to denuclearize Iran.
He's not been able to uh effect regime
change in Iran. So Iran still exists and
uh it's slightly weakened or something
but it's still there. So that's that's
been a setback for Mr. Netanyahu and Mr.
Netanyahu is facing various political
troubles at home uh corruption cases and
all. So it's a pretty tight situation
for for him. Uh I don't really
know how long Mr. Nathan may last you
know because see the entire nation came
with him because of the war with Iran.
But now that the war is over definitely
and uh Gaza also is not Hamas is also
not a big threat now compared to what it
was in October 2023.
Uh I don't know.
So what what happens going forward? I
think there should be a ceasefire and
some kind of secession of hostilities in
Gaza. Obviously it's a human
humanitarian disaster. I am not blaming
Israel for starting the war in the
aftermath of that horrific terrorist
attack. You cannot ever
um justify or support or or
condone terrorism. So Israel did the
right thing. Maybe they can now do a
ceasefire and ensure that you know uh
Hamas they will have to ensure that
Hamas doesn't exist. So Hamas obviously
from Israel's perspective needs to be
wiped out and if they feel satisfied
that that is done then maybe they can go
ahead with the ceasefire. Um yeah so
that's the deal right now. Let's see in
what direction this goes.
Right.
Sumit Agarwal says
are Indians stuck between remembering
their glorious past and embracing
modernity.
A lot of Indians are stuck
singing glories of the past and uh they
refuse to to recognize the fact that
India is not a glorious nation today and
a lot needs to be done to make India you
know strong again and and let's say
glorious again a lot of Indians just
want to keep on harping about the past
and and you know I am accused of being
one of those people because I keep
reminding people about the fact that
India was once a great nation India was
once the nation with the highest GDP in
in the highest highest share of the GDP
across the world and so on. The reason I
remind people of this is because I want
Indians to shed their inferiority
complex.
It's not because I am stuck in the past.
So Indians need to be practical and
pragmatic. Do remind yourselves of the
greatness of your past of what your
ancestors achieved but remember it has
all been destroyed.
The reason to remember what your
ancestors achieved in the glory of the
past, it's important because that will
help you shed your godamned inferiority
complex. Indians have a tremendous
inferiority complex and that really
annoys me like anything. And that's what
I'm trying to do. But remember, there's
a tremendous amount of work to be done
and you have to embrace modernity. And
modernity doesn't mean that you have to
embrace becoming becoming more vested
every day. you have to embrace
technology, embrace all the benefits of
technology without becoming culturally
dominated by the west. So yeah, Indians
are kind of stuck in this loop and uh
and one of the reasons is that we we
aren't taught how to think critically
and that's why you know you're stuck
here and there and you you neither here
nor there.
Okay. Right. Um,
Kasik Biswas says, "With Trump recently
reiterating his intent to pressure US
tech companies to stop hiring from
India, how do you assess the political
the potential impact or on the future of
H1B visa holders and aspiring tech
professionals? If this sentiment gains
traction, what opportunities is it
present for India to not just retain top
talent but also strengthen its domestic
technology and innovation ecosystem?" So
Trump obviously wants everything to be
MAGA, make America great again, which
means you know all the jobs should be uh
American jobs, stop hiring foreigners,
stop hiring Indians, uh clamp down on
the H-1B program and so on so forth. Uh
so if he actually goes ahead with that,
it will be bad for the Indians who hold
H1B visas who may be asked to go back
possibly. It'll be also bad for Indians
who are aspiring H1B visa applicants and
who want to go and work in the US. It'll
be bad for them as also. Yeah. So, so
does it provide if this actually does
gain traction does it provide
opportunities for India to retain top
talent? I don't think so. As long as
India doesn't solve the problems at
home, the top talent will go somewhere
else. They will go to Europe. They'll go
to Australia. Look, people want a good
life. People want
merit and talent to be recognized in
India the way the shape and form it is
right it is in right now India doesn't
recognize or respect merit or talent
India the Indian system seeks out and
destroys talent it seeks out and
destroys merit
the Indian system worships mediocrity
and that's why Indians won't leave any
self-respecting Indian who is talented
wants to leave because they want a good
life. They want to earn earn money to
their full potential.
If you are a top class scientist, okay,
or or engineer and you you want to serve
the country, you want to win, but you
get this salary and with the same
qualifications and talent, you will get
that salary in the US. I mean, why not,
right? Why sacrifice your hopes and
aspirations for the sake of a country
that doesn't even like you? Not not
country but but system that actually
hates you. Especially if you're general
category or whatever. So that's why
Indians leave. Now if the Americans stop
the H1B or clam on on the H1B on H1B
visa, Indians will look for other
opportunities. Maybe in the UK, maybe in
the EU, maybe in Australia, maybe even
China, who knows? God knows what. That's
so until and unless the government of
India fixes the problems at home, it
does this doesn't present any
opportunity for India. Okay. So India is
going to have to fix that. India needs
to reward merit. Right now India is all
about reservations and God knows what
else. And the education system is broken
and the whole system is broken. Until
that's fixed, nothing is going to
change. Okay? And it will not reverse
the brain drain.
Okay? So we have come to the end of
today's questions. I have a few more but
I'll take some questions from the live
chat. Now let me see.
So if you have questions I'll take a few
questions
uh from the live chat over the next uh
few minutes. Let's see
what else. Um okay Kesh Koshik says to
the souls question. I think we can
consider beings other than humans in the
process of reincarnation. Well, there we
have an answer. There we have an answer.
Very interesting. I think we can
consider beings other than humans as
being in the process of reincarnation.
For example, when I die, it's not like
I'll reincarnate in a human body. Maybe
I can be a bird or maybe a bird if it uh
satisfies certain criteria, it can
reincarnate as human being. Okay, there
we have it.
There we have it. Good. I think that's a
good good answer to that to that
question. Um anonymous scientist says
Donald J. Trump has just now posted on
truth social that he will announce a
ceasefire between Cambodia and Thailand
just like India Pakistan ceasefire. He
gave example of India Pakistan again.
Well that's what Donald Donald Trump
does. That's what it does. Yeah. Anyway,
let's see how that goes. Let's see how
that goes.
Akash says uh what's the importance of a
think tank for a nation? Do Indian think
tanks have real influence on national
policy and is it a good idea to create a
new think tank? So what's a think tank?
First of all, it's a group of people who
come together and who and and they they
generally are not just any random
people. They're generally people from
the academic field or academic field or
some specialized field and they all come
together pull their minds together and
they come up with policy proposals and
do do detailed research about various
issues and then those policy proposals
can be given to the government as as
solutions to various problems the
country is facing and maybe those people
can be commissioned by the government or
by companies to to provide answers to
some questions or provide solutions to
problems. So that's what a think tank
is. Uh so it can be important for a
nation if if it does indeed provide
valuable uh answers to pressing
questions and if it if it provides
highquality solutions to important
problems. In that case think tank is
good. Uh we have some think tanks in
India. I'm not sure what they do. I'm
not sure what they do. So you can have a
think tank
in which you have a bunch of let's say
five 10 people and maybe you you're not
serving the nation maybe you serving
whoever commisss you. So maybe you have
people who are good at data analysis uh
machine learning um geopolitical
forecasting perhaps and uh business
forecasting. You bring people from
disparate disciplines together, combine
their their talents together and then
maybe you can be commissioned. We can be
hired by a company, major company to
understand the geopolitical risk climate
over the next 6 months or 1 year or 3
years and provide solutions to specific
problems. And that can be a very
valuable lucrative, you know, thing to
do if you have that sort of a think
tank. And once again, you can have think
tanks that are national think tanks and
that advise the nation, the government
on policy. So if you can genuinely
provide highquality answers to pressing
questions and if you can genu genuinely
provide highquality solutions to big
problems, then yeah, it makes sense to
create a think tank. So that's that's
what a think tank is. Uh I'm not sure
about the quality of think tanks in this
country. Some may be good, I suppose.
Some I don't know what they do.
Okay.
Right now,
Mlevin says, "Is the Thailand Cambodia
issue a proxy war of the US and China?"
That remains to be seen. It the origin
is a temple dispute. That's not a proxy
war between anybody. That's a temple
dispute. It's a very ancient historical
dispute.
But now it could morph into something
else. So that's that remains to be seen
because like I explained Thailand is on
the US side, Cambodia is on the Chinese
side. That's the kind of influence you
have and China has invested in both
countries billions of dollars for its
belt and road initiative. So China is in
a kind of dilemma that I can't take
sides and so on and obviously there are
local regional political reasons for
this as well. So we'll have to see.
We'll have to see. We'll have to wait
and watch.
Um, Senior File says, "Who's the
pound-for-pound best MMA fighter right
now?" I am not watching MMA these days.
I would love to, but um I'm I'm not I'm
not keeping up with what's happening.
So, I don't know. I'm not sure right
now.
Yeah.
Okay.
Amisha says, "From boycotting Maldives
to giving loan to Maldives, we have come
a long way." Well, the sentiment of
boycotting the Maldives was public
sentiment. The government of India never
expressed any such sentiment that we
should boycott Maldives or any any such
thing. So, India, the government of
India adopted a very mature foreign
policy when it came to dealing with the
Maldives and now we are giving a loan to
the Maldives and we have indeed come a
long way. So, you are right. Absolutely.
Okay. Okay, let us let's take
um
do we have any other questions? Um
Lucario says, "I said cookies are not
Indians on Reddit and Reddit banned my
account permanently." Well, you will see
that most of the Reddit subreddits are
anti-India and they're run by either
Pakistanis or Bangladesh or God knows
what. So, yeah, not surprised. Of
course, they aren't Indians.
They their their origin is is the Chin
region of the the the Yunan region of
China. They're not even Burmese. And
forget about the ethnic origins. You
need to have allegiance
to a country, right? You need to have
respect for the country's culture and
civilization and you cannot
fight as a proxy of somebody else
against the country that you're living
in. So yeah, it's a big problem for
India.
Okay.
Okay. M Cleven says, "Did you watch the
F1 movie? Do you watch the F1 sport?" As
a kid in the 80s, I used to sometimes
when I was outside of India, living
outside of India, I used to sometimes
watch F1. I didn't really know much
about it, but it was like kind of fun to
see those cars zipping around. I haven't
seen the F1 movie. I wanted to watch it,
but I think I missed it. So, I've heard
it's good. Okay, with that, I think I
will end today's live stream. Thank you
so much for all the questions. Tomorrow
I'm doing another live stream, a super
chat live stream. Lots of people have
asked for it, so let's do it. So if you
have questions that you would like to
ask me on the super chat live stream,
please do tune in tomorrow and I look
forward to seeing you there. So please
keep asking questions, keep learning,
and never stop raising your standards.
I'll see you soon tomorrow. Thank you.
Bye-bye.